Congratulations are definitely in order.
당연히 축하해야죠
Yesterday was a mammoth first day on this course and you got through it.
어제는 이 코스에서 엄청난 첫날을 보냈고 그걸 해냈죠
You set up your environment and we're off to the races.
환경만 설정하면 바로 레이스가 시작되죠
So as I recap, what you can now do is use a llama to run models locally.
복습해보면, 이제 할 수 있는 건 llama를 이용해 로컬 모델을 실행하는 거죠
You can call OpenAI's API to run a frontier model.
OpenAI API를 통해 개척자 모델을 실행할 수 있죠
You understand, at least at a high level, the difference between a system and a user prompt.
적어도 상위 레벨에서는 시스템과 사용자 프롬프트의 차이를 이해하죠
And you've built a summarization use case, which is an important commercial application.
요약 사용 사례를 구축했는데 중요한 상업적 응용 프로그램이죠
Today we're going to talk a bit about what are the steps to get to being an LLM engineer, set you up
오늘은 LLM 엔지니어가 되기 위해 어떤 단계를 거쳐야 하는지 얘기해 보겠습니다 성공을 위한
for success, and then talk more about frontier models.
준비 과정과 비트를 이용한 모델에 대해 더 얘기해 보죠
That is the plan.
그게 계획이에요
Now, let me start by just emphasizing that this course, this eight week course is a practical course.
먼저 강조하고 싶은 건 이 8주 과정의 실용성이에요
First and foremost we're going to cover theory.
가장 먼저 이론에 대해 배울 거예요
We're going to cover the foundational information that you need.
여러분이 필요한 기본 정보를 다룰 거예요
But we're always going to do it in a practical context.
하지만 실용적인 맥락에서 할 거예요
I'm a big believer in the best way to learn is by doing.
전 실전이야말로 최고의 배움이라고 믿어요
And that's what we'll be actually doing.
그게 우리가 할 일이죠
And we're going to be putting it to good use.
좋은 일에 쓸 거예요
We're going to be building commercial projects as we go.
상업 프로젝트를 진행할 거예요
And I'll often be asking you to try and think about how you could apply what you've learned to your
여기서 배운 것을 본업에 어떻게 적용할지 생각해 보라고 할
day job and try and build little prototypes to bring that to life.
때가 많아요 그걸 구현할 시제품을 만들어 보세요
So that is the flavour of the course.
이게 이 코스의 맛이에요
There are three different aspects to LM engineering that you'll be picking up as we go.
LM 엔지니어링에는 세 가지 다른 양상이 있습니다 진행하면서 알게 되실 텐데요
The first of them is just understanding the models that are out there, the wide range of different
첫 번째는 모델을 이해하는 겁니다 다양한 유형의 광범위한 LM과
types of LM and what they're capable of, whether we're talking about open source versions, the closed
어떤 게 가능한지를요 오픈 소스 버전이든 폐쇄 소스 유료 버전이든
source paid versions, ones that are multi-modal, that can generate images or audio, the different
이미지나 오디오를 생성할 수 있는 다중 모듈인 것이든 LMS의 다양한
architectures of LMS, and importantly, how you pick which LM you should be working with in the first
아키텍처든 가장 먼저 어떤 LM을 어떻게 선택해야 하는지를요
We'll be looking at all of the tools of the trade, things like the ubiquitous hugging face, the super
모든 툴을 살펴볼 겁니다 안아주는 얼굴이라든지 랑게인
impressive glue code in Lange chain, the fabulous gradio that you will see.
접착 코드도 있고 멋진 그라디오도 있죠
I'm a big fan of weights and biases.
전 무게와 편견을 좋아해요
Super helpful and then modal for deploying it to production.
생산으로 배포하는 데 큰 도움이 되죠
And we'll be looking at techniques different ways that you can apply this.
다양한 기술을 적용할 수 있는 방법을 살펴볼 거예요
The field of AI to solve business problems from using API's Rag which is such a hot topic, fine tuning
인공지능 분야는 API 래그를 이용해 비즈니스 문제를 해결합니다 API는 뜨거운 주제죠 미세
and then at the end a full Agentic AI solution.
조정하고 최종적으로는 에이전트식 AI 솔루션이죠
The idea of this course is that I've planned it so that it will apply almost no matter what your level
이 코스는 여러분의 경험 수준에 상관없이 적용될 수 있도록
of experience.
계획했어요
You may find initially that some of the first few weeks are too simplistic for you, or the first few
처음 몇 주는 너무 단순하다고 느끼실 겁니다 처음 며칠은요
And there I would say hang in there, use it as a way to just sort of reinforce some of the of the foundational
여기서 잠깐 기다리세요 기본 정보를 강화하는 방법으로 사용하세요
information that we'll talk a bit more detail about things like tokens than you've done before, perhaps.
토큰 같은 것에 대해 좀 더 자세히 얘기할 테니까요
So there'll be stuff to pick up, but you can go through it quickly and then make the projects your
배울 게 많겠지만 재빨리 훑어보고 자신의 프로젝트로 만들 수 있어요
own.
그러니 이 경험을 토대로 더 심오한 버전을 만들고 앞으로 있을 더 어렵고 재밌는 프로젝트를
coming up later.
준비하세요
If it feels too challenging, then please, please don't worry.
너무 힘들면 걱정하지 마세요
Take your time with the practicals.
실용적인 건 천천히 공부하세요
Take your time with the exercises.
천천히 연습하세요
Work your way through them.
잘 헤쳐나가세요
There are some extra guides that I'll talk about in week one that would help give you a sort of firmer
첫째 주에 더 자세히 알려드릴 가이드도 있어요 더 탄탄한 기반을 마련해
footing if you need it.
줄 거예요
And please, please, please ask for help.
제발, 제발 도움을 청해 주세요
I am here, I respond quickly.
난 신속하게 대응해요
You can always reach out to me, either as I say on the platform or through email or through LinkedIn.
언제든 제게 연락하세요 플랫폼이나 이메일 또는 링크드인을 통해서요
Details are in the GitHub repo.
깃허브 압류에 자세한 내용이 있어요
Reach out to me.
내게 연락해요
Get help.
Get it, get it, 도움 요청해요
That is what I'm here for.
그래서 제가 온 거예요
And then if it feels just right, then excellent.
느낌이 괜찮으면 더 좋고요
Keep going.
계속해요
So the prerequisite is beginner to intermediate level Python.
필수 조건은 초보자에서 중급 레벨 파이썬 을 지원하는 것인데요
And if you have intermediate level Python you're going to find it easiest and you'll get the most out
중간 레벨의 파이썬 을 가지고 있다면 가장 쉽게 찾을 수 있고 가장 많은 것을 얻을 수
of it.
있어요.
And if you look for example at this line of code right here, which is just a random line from within
예를 들어 여기 이 코드 줄을 보시면 함수 내부의 무작위 선이죠
If you basically know what that's probably doing, then you're in great shape if you know exactly what
그게 뭘 하는 건지 안다면 아주 좋은 겁니다 그게 정확히 뭘 하는
it's doing and if you know in fact why, it's not perhaps the most optimal way of doing it, then you're
건지 알고 그 이유를 안다면 최적의 방법은 아닐 수도 있어요 그럼 그 이상인
more than more than, well set that you're advanced, and that's great if you don't know what this does
거죠 고급으로 설정할 겁니다 이게 뭘 하는지 모르고 yild이나
and you're not familiar with a world with a word like yield or set or the dot get, then there is a
set이나 .get 같은 단어가 익숙하지 않다면 특별한 공책이 있어요 첫 주에 Jupyter
special notebook, a special Jupyter Lab in week one for you, which is a guide to to Python at this
랩을 특별히 보여드리는 거죠 이 레벨에서 파이썬에 대한 가이드예요
And as you go through that notebook, I will take you through each of the stepping stones until we get
여러분이 그 노트를 보는 동안 저는 디딤돌을 하나씩 짚어 나가며 이런 선이 말이 되는
to a point where a line like this should make sense.
지점을 찾을 거예요. Get it.
And of course, you can also use ChatGPT and Claude.
물론 챗GPT와 클로드도 사용할 수 있어요
The the the genies are really good at explaining code.
지니는 코드를 정말 잘 설명해요
And indeed, if you put something like this in there, they would tell you exactly what it does and
실제로 이런 걸 넣으면 어떤 작용을 하는지 그 이유를 설명하고
why and step you through it too.
설명해주죠
And they're probably just as good as, as my, my notebook.
제 노트만큼이나 잘 썼을 거예요
So either way, that should give you what you need to do.
어느 쪽이든 필요한 건 다 얻었어요
And at any point, if you don't understand some code, you can always use ChatGPT.
그리고 언제든 어떤 코드를 이해 못 하겠으면 챗GPT를 이용하세요
So to get the most out of this course, there are a few things that I would ask you.
이 코스를 최대한 활용하기 위해 몇 가지 물어볼게요. Get it.
First of all, follow along as I do my coding.
먼저, 제가 코딩하는 걸 잘 따라오세요
So when I'm when I'm going through in the labs and I'm executing cells, then either at the same time
랩에서 셀을 실행할 때 동시에 또는 나중에
or afterwards go through and do it yourself.
직접 할 수 있죠
And if you hit snafus, which you might do for various reasons, then have a crack at trying to to sort
여러 이유로 스내퍼스를 누르면 그 이유를 알아내려고 노력하세요
Do some debugging.
디버깅을 하죠
That's a great way to learn and complete the exercises, and then put your code examples up on GitHub.
학습하고 연습을 완료하는 훌륭한 방법이죠 코드 예제를 깃허브에 올리는 거예요
It's actually a great way as well.
사실 좋은 방법이에요
If you're new to this space, and you're trying to build up something of a kind of resume to show that
이 분야에 처음 들어왔고 이 분야에서 쌓은 경험을 자랑하려고 이력서를
you've built some of this experience, the best kind of resume you can have is a GitHub repo, because
작성하고 싶다면 깃허브 리포토가 가장 좋습니다 사람들이 그걸 보고 여러분이
people will look at it and will see the sorts of things you've worked on.
작업한 걸 볼 테니까요
And of course, you don't want to put exactly the projects we do.
물론 우리가 하는 것과 똑같은 것을 Put 하면 안 되죠
You want to make them your own.
자신의 것으로 만들고 싶죠
You want to figure out, okay, how can I apply this to my business area or to a personal project that
이걸 어떻게 비즈니스 영역이나 작업 중인 개인 프로젝트에 적용할 수 있는지
I'm working on to make it something that's similar, slightly different?
알아내야 하죠 유사하거나 약간 다른 것으로요
Take on it for new business value.
새 사업 가치를 위해서요
That is a great way to get the most out of this course, and then look to share your code.
이 코스에서 가장 많은 걸 얻을 수 있는 방법이죠 코드를 공유하도록 하세요 get it
If you're happy with it and you and you're okay with that.
본인 마음에 들면 그걸로 된 거예요
I've got instructions about how you can submit a pull request, which means that I can see your code.
끌어오기 요청을 어떻게 제출할지 지침이 있어요 코드를 볼 수 있다는 뜻이죠
I can give you feedback on it if you'd like, and I can also then republish it so that other students
원하시면 피드백을 드릴 수도 있고 다시 게시할 수도 있습니다 이 과정을 듣는 다른
taking the course will see your examples and we can all share in it together.
학생들이 여러분의 예를 보고 함께 공유할 수 있도록요
And of course stick at it.
물론 계속 노력해야죠
Hang on in there.
조금만 참아요
This course gets better and better and better, I assure you.
이 코스는 점점 더 좋아져요
And I you know, there's there's going to be so many projects, so much commercial application.
앞으로 많은 프로젝트와 상업적 응용 프로그램이 있을 거예요
And I definitely encourage you to stay the course.
코스를 지키라고 응원할게요
And the thing I didn't put down here one more time is that getting the most out of the course.
한 가지 더 말씀드리자면 MTB를 최대한 활용해야 해요 TMI, TMI, MTB F1
Also, please reach out to me if I can help at any point.
그리고 제가 도울 일이 있으면 언제든 연락 주세요